Kenneth Roby Mexican Documents Collection 1788-1917(bulk 1824-1857)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Kenneth Roby Mexican Documents Collection 1788-1917 bulk 1824-1857
MS 449
Roby, Kenneth
Kenneth Roby Mexican Documents Collection, 1788-1917 (Bulk 1824-1857),contains seven series of documents that were written and distributed by various federal, state, and local government officials in Mexico between late 18th Century and early 20th Century. This collection also contains a small series of documents that were written and distributed by Spanish and English government officials in their colonies between late 19th Century and early 20th Century. Overall, this decree and orders collection includes military correspondence, constitutions and laws, appointments and promotions in the government. The collection also includes a chronological list of political leaders, important events, financial issues such as taxes and budgets, and overall customs in Mexico.
13 Linear Feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
Significant eras mentioned in this collection include Spanish and English colonial periods in Mexico, Cuba, and Dominica; Mexican war of Independence; first Mexican Empire under Agustin de Iturbide; early Mexican Republic; political domination of Antonio Lopez De Santa Anna; Mexican- American War; second Mexican Empire under Maximilian I; French intervention in Mexico; political domination of Porfirio Diaz; and Mexican Revolution. Individuals mentioned include Agustin De Iturbide, Anastasio Bustamante, Antonio Lopez De Santa Anna, Ramon Gutierrez Del Mazo, Luis Quintanar, Manuel De la Sota Riva, Manuel Gomez Pedraza, Jose Antonio De Andrade, Francisco Molinos Del Campo, Melchor Muzquiz, Estevan De Munuera, Jose Maria Calderon, Juan Gonzalez Cabofranco, Joaquin De Haro Y Tamariz, Patricio Furlong, Guadalupe Victoria, Jose Ignacio Esteva, Jose Maria Tornel, Antonio De Zamacona, Felix Neccechea, Jose Maria De Guadalupe Pavon, Felipe Codallos, Isidro Reyes, Juan Mugica y Osorio, Cosme Furlong, Francisco Perez. Locations mentioned include Pueblo, Mexico City, Districto Federal, Sonora, Sinaloa, Tlaxcala and Tlapa Territories, Cuba, and Dominica.
Organization
This collection is organized into 7 series.
Series I: Late Colonial Period in Mexico, 1788-1820
Series II: Independence - First Mexican Empire, 1821-1824
Series III: Early Mexican Republic, 1824-1835
Series IV: Santa Anna Era - Mexican American War, 1836-1857
Series V: Emperor Maximilian I - French Intervention, 1863-1864
Series VI: Porfiriato - Mexican Revolution, 1907-1917
Series VII: Islands under Spanish - English Control, 1884-1917
Scope and Content Note
The first and second series in this collection contain various decrees, public announcements, and orders written between 1788 and 1824. These documents summarize certain events that occurred at the end of Spanish control in Mexico, the Mexican War of Independence and the beginning of the First Mexican Empire. The decrees and orders in this collection are written by important Viceroys of New Spain, Captain Generals, Intendants, Political Chiefs of Puebla and México, and officials from the Ministry of Finance and Relations. The third and fourth series contain the bulk of the material in this collection. These documents, written between 1824 and 1857, summarize certain events that occurred during the early phase of the Mexican Republic, Santa Anna’s political domination and Mexican- American War. The decrees and orders in this collection are written by Presidents, Governors, Advisers, Prefects, Superior Court Officials, and secretaries from Puebla and Mexico. There are also decrees and orders written by officials from the Ministry of War and Navy, Finance, Foreign Relations, Interior, and Justice, and by Captain Generals and Political Chiefs from Tlaxcala and Tlapa territories in Mexico. The fifth series in this collection contain various decrees, public announcements, and orders written between 1863 and 1864.These documents summarize certain events that occurred in Mexico during the political intervention of Emperor Maximilian I and the French. The decrees and orders in this collection are written by Advisers, Secretaries, and Prefects in Puebla; as well as, some French Military Officers. The sixth series in this collection contains various decrees, public announcements, and orders written between 1907 and 1917. These documents summarize certain events that occurred in Mexico before and after the Mexican Revolution. This series contains the Constitution of 1917, Mexican State laws, and decrees in State Newspapers from Sinaloa and Sonora. Lastly, the seventh series in this collection contains various decrees, laws, public announcements, and orders written between 1884 and 1917. These documents follow Spanish and English colonial periods in Mexico, Cuba, and Dominica.
Puebla, Mexico records (MS 004), 1655-1898 (Bulk 1840-1898);Collection related to Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico (MS 108), 1847-1967 (Bulk 1853-1867); Broadsides from Mexico Collection (MS 339), 1676-1927 (Bulk 1820-1927)
Administrative Law -- Mexico.; Elections -- Mexico -- History.; Generals -- Mexico.; Governors -- Mexico.; Mexico -- History -- Spanish Colony, 1540-1810.; Mexico -- History -- Wars of Independence, 1810-1821.; Mexico -- History -- 1821-1861.; Mexican War, 1846-1848.; Mexico--History--European Intervention, 1861-1867.; Mexico -- Politics and Government -- 1867-1910.; Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920.; Puebla (Mexico: State) -- Politics and Government.; Sonora (Mexico: State) -- Politics and Government.; Sinaloa (Mexico: State) -- Politics and Government.; Cuba--Politics and government.; Dominica--Politics and government.
Container List
- Series I: Late Colonial Period in Mexico, 1788-1820
  This series is divided into three subseries. The subseries are arranged chronically by political figures (Viceroys and Intendants) and the years they served. There are also various orders and public announcements arranged chronologically by year.
  - Subseries 1: Viceroys of New Spain
    - Miguel Joseph De Azanza, 1799-1800 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Felix Berenguer De Marquina, 1800-1802 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Joseph De Yturrigaray, 1803-1807 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pedro Garibay, 1808-1809 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Francisco Xavier De Lizana, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pedro Catani, 1810 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Francisco Xavier Venegas, 1810-1812 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Juan Ruiz De Apodaca, 1819-1820 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: Intendants of Puebla Province
    - Manuel De Flon, 1800; 1808 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ciriaco Del Llano, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Various Orders - Public Announcements
    - 1788, 1790, 1819-1820 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Independence - First Mexican Empire, 1821-1824
  This series is divided into four subseries. The subseries are arranged chronically by political figures (Captain Generals, Political Chiefs, and Ministers) and the years they served. There are also various public announcements and news arranged chronologically by year.
  - Subseries 1: Captain Generals - Political Chiefs of Puebla
    - Carlos Garcia, 1821-1822 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Jose Maria Moran, 1822-1823 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Jose Maria Calderon, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Various Orders - Public Announcements
    - Congressional Diaries (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Bulletins - Puebla (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 3: Captain Generals - Political Chiefs of Mexico
    - Agustin De Iturbide, 1821 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Anastasio Bustamante, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ramon Gutierrez Del Mazo, 1821-1822 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Luis Quintanar, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Manuel De La Sota Riva, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Manuel Gomez Pedraza, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Jose Antonio De Andrade, 1822-1823 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Francisco Molinos Del Campo, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Melchor Muzquiz, 1823-1824 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 4: Ministry of Finance - Relations
    - Antonio De Medina, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lucas Alaman, 1823 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series III: Early Mexican Republic, 1824-1835
  This series is divided into six subseries. The subseries are arranged chronically by political figures (Governors, Secretaries, Prefects, and Ministers) and the years they served. There are also various News Bulletins, Manifestos, and Laws arranged chronologically by year.
  - Subseries 1: Governors of Puebla
    - Estevan De Munuera, 1824 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Jose Maria Calderon, 1825-1827 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Juan Gonzalez Cabofranco, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Joaquin De Haro Y Tamariz, 1828 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Patricio Furlong, 18291833 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Juan Jose Andrade, 1830-1832 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - Guadalupe Victoria, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Manuel Rincon, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2: Governors of Mexico - Federal District
    - Melchor Muzquiz, 1824-1826 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Francisco Molinos Del Campo, 1826 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Juan Manuel De Elizalde, 1826-1827 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Jose Ignacio Esteva, 18271830 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Jose Maria Tornel, 1828-1829 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Miguel Cervantes, 18301832 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Ignacio Martinez, 1832-1833 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Jose Joaquin De Herrera, 1833 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3: Secretaries - Prefects in Puebla
    - Antonio De Zamacona, 1830 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Felix Neccechea, 1830 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Francisco Maria Tamayo, 1830 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jose Maria De Guadalupe Pavon, 1832-1833 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jose Maria Fernandez, 18301835 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 4: National News Bulletins - Manifestos
    - Circulated in Puebla, 1827-18281830 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Circulated in Mexico, 1826 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 5: National/State Laws - Government Proceedings
    - Circulated in Puebla, 18261830 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Circulated in Mexico, 1826 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 6: Ministry of Finance - Foreign Relations
    - Jose Ignacio Esteva, 1825 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jose Ignacio Pavon, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Jose Maria Ortiz Monsaterio, 1832 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Santa Anna Era – Mexican American War, 1836-1857
  This series is divided into thirteen subseries. The subseries are arranged chronically by political figures (Generals-Presidents, Governors, Advisers, Prefects, Superior Court Officials, Secretaries, Captain Generals, Political Chiefs and Ministers) and the years they served. There are also various News Bulletins, Manifestos, and Laws arranged chronologically by year.
  - Subseries 1: Generals-Presidents of Mexico
    - Anastasio Bustamante, 1841 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Antonio Lopez De Santa Anna, 184218461853 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Governors of Puebla
    - Jose Antonio Mozo, 1836 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Felipe Codallos, 1837-18391841 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Joaquin De Haro Y Tamariz, 1841 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Juan Gonzalez Cabofranco, 1837-18391844-1845 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Valentin Canalizo, 1842 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Jose Joaquin Reyes, 1843 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Isidro Reyes, 1842-1844 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Domingo Ibarra, 1846-1847 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Juan Mugica y Osorio, 1848-1853 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Cosme Furlong, 1853 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Jose Maria Gonzalez Mendoza, 1853 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Francisco Ibarra, 1855 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Juan Traconis, 1856 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Jose Garcia Conde, 1857 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Francisco Perez, 1853-1855 (Box 8-9)
  - Subseries 3: Advisers - Prefects in Puebla
    - Rafael Espinosa, 1839 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Jose Mariano Castillero, 1841 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Jose Juan Llufriu, 1843-1844 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Francisco Calderon, 1844 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Miguel Tagle, 1845 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Gabriel Rodriguez, 1846 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Manuel Joaquin Perez Salazar, 1848 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Jose Ildefonso Amable, 1848 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Jose Maria De Guadalupe Pavon, 1848-18491853 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Jose Maria Marin, 1849 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Miguel Maria De La Rosa, 1851 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Manuel Ignacio Loaiza, 1853 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Jose Rafael Isunza, 1853 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Jose Maria Gonzalez Mendoza, 1853-1855 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Luis De La Vega, 1854-1855 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 4: Superior Court Officials in Puebla
    - Juan Ybarra, 1841 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Juan Pedro Necoechea, 1849-18511855 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 5: Secretaries of Puebla
    - Jose Maria Fernandez, 1837184118491853 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Pedro De Azuce Y Zalvide, 1839 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Pedro Jose De Aguirre, 1841 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Manuel Zetina Abad, 1846 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Jose Octaviano De La Rosa, 1853 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Sebastian Lesina, 1853 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Joaquin Maria De Uriarte, 1853-1855 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Pedro Torres Y Larrainzar, 1853-1855 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Jose Antonio Perez Marin, 1854-1855 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 6: National News Bulletins - Manifestos
    - Circulated in Puebla, 18411843184618491851 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Circulated in Mexico, 18351838-18391841-1842 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 7: National/State Laws - Government Proceedings
    - Circulated in Puebla, 18371841184618511853 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Circulated in Mexico, 18381841 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 8: Ministry of War - Navy
    - Jose Moran, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Jose Maria Tornel, 1838-18391841 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Juan Nepomuceno Almonte, 1841 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 9: Ministry of Finance
    - Jose Maria De Bocanegra, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Manuel Eduardo De Gorostiza, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Pedro Jose De Echeverría, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Jose Gomez De La Cortina, 1839 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Santiago Sartorio, 1841 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Manuel Maria Canseco, 1841 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Domingo Dufoo, 1841 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Ignacio Trigueros, 1841-1843 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 10: Ministry of Interior
    - Jose Antonio Romero, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Jose Joaquin Pesado, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - J. De Iturbide, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Manuel Eduardo De Gorostiza, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Jose Maria Jimenez, 1841 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Teodosio Lares, 1853 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 11: Ministry of Justice
    - Crispiniano Del Castillo, 1841 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Manuel Baranda, 1843 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Teodosio Lares, 1853-1855 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 12: Captain Generals - Political Chiefs of Tlaxcala/Tlapa Territories
    - Jose Ignacio De Ormaechea, 18491851 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Jose Miguel Sanchez De La Vega, 1854 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 13: Clergy Manifestos
    - Clemente De Jesus Munguia- Bishop of Michoacan, 1855 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series V: Emperor Maximilian I - French Intervention, 1863-1864
  This series is divided into three subseries. The subseries are arranged chronically by political figures (Advisers, Prefects, Secretaries, and French Military Officers) and the years they served.
  - Subseries 1: Advisers - Prefects in Puebla
    - Fernando Pardo, 1863-1864 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Juan De Uriarte, 1863-1864 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2: Secretaries of Puebla
    - Manuel Marchena, 1863-1864 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Francisco Daza, 1863-1864 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 3: French Military Officers
    - Colonel Brincourt, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - General Forey, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Series VI: Porfiriato - Mexican Revolution, 1907-1917
  This series is divided into two subseries. These subseries contain Newspapers, Laws and a Constitution that are arranged chronologically by year.
  - Subseries 1: Constitution - State Laws
    - Constitution of 1917- Venustiano Carranza (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Sonora, 1907 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Sinaloa, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Decrees in State Newspapers
    - Sonora, July- Dec 1912 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
    - Sonora, Jan- Oct 1915 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
- Series VII: Islands under Spanish - English Control, 1884-1917
  This series is divided into two subseries and arranged chronologically by year.
  - Subseries 1: Cuba- Laws
    - Mining Legislation, 1884 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Licensing Regulations, 1886 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: Dominica-Governors - Legislative Council
    - H. Hesketh Bell, 1914-1915 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Arthur Mahaffy, 1916 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - T.A.V. Best, 1915-1917 (Box 13, Folder 3)